<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The just mans justification: or A letter by way of plea in barre; written by L. Col. John Lilburne. to the Honrble Justice Reeves, one of the justices of the Common-wealths courts, commonly called Common Pleas wherein the sinister and indirect practises of Col. Edward King against L. Col. Lilburne, are discovered. 1. In getting him cast into prison for maxy [sic] weekes together, without prosecuting any charge against him. 2. In arresting him upon a groundlesse action of two thousand pound in the Court of Common Pleas; thereby to evade and take off L. C. Lilburns testimony to the charge of high treason given in against Col. King, and now depending before the Honourable House of Commons hereunto annexed. In which letter is fully asserted and proved that this cause is only tryable in Parliament, and not in any subordinate court of justice whatsoever.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 107 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88208</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E407_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202758</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862942</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862942</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88208)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E407[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The just mans justification: or A letter by way of plea in barre; written by L. Col. John Lilburne. to the Honrble Justice Reeves, one of the justices of the Common-wealths courts, commonly called Common Pleas wherein the sinister and indirect practises of Col. Edward King against L. Col. Lilburne, are discovered. 1. In getting him cast into prison for maxy [sic] weekes together, without prosecuting any charge against him. 2. In arresting him upon a groundlesse action of two thousand pound in the Court of Common Pleas; thereby to evade and take off L. C. Lilburns testimony to the charge of high treason given in against Col. King, and now depending before the Honourable House of Commons hereunto annexed. In which letter is fully asserted and proved that this cause is only tryable in Parliament, and not in any subordinate court of justice whatsoever.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, with divers additions presented as a necessary apologie by the author, to all the commons of England, but especially to the private soldiers of his Excellency, Sir Thomas Fairfax his Army, August 1647.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Variant: has "maxy" corrected to "many".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber 28. 1647".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Prisoners and prisons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE IVST MANS IVSTIFICATION: OR A Letter by way of Plea in Barre;</head>
            <head type="sub">Written by L. Col. <hi>John Lilburne.</hi> to the Honr<hi rend="sup">ble</hi> Juſtice <hi>Reeves,</hi> one of the Iuſtices of the Common-wealths Courts, commonly called Common Pleas</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Wherein the ſiniſter and indirect practiſes of Col. <hi>Edward King</hi> againſt L. Col <hi>Lilburne,</hi> are diſcovered.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1.</hi> In getting him cast into priſon for many weekes together, without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting any charge againſt him.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2.</hi> In arreſting him upon a groundleſſe action of two thouſand pound in the Court of Common Pleas; thereby to evade and take off L. C. <hi>Lilburns</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the charge of high Treaſon given in againſt Col. <hi>King,</hi> and now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending before the Honourable Houſe of Commons hereunto annexed.</p>
               <p>In which Letter is fully aſſerted and proved that this cauſe is only tryable in Parliament, and not in any ſubordinate Court of juſtice whatſoever.</p>
            </argument>
            <head>The ſecond Edition, with divers Additions preſented as a neceſſary Apologie by the Author, to all the Commons of England, but eſpecially to the Private Soldiers of his Excellency, Sir Thomas Fairfax his Army, Auguſt 1647.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Levit. 19.15</hi>
                  </bibl>
Yee ſhall doe no unrighteouſneſſe in Iudgement, thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honour the perſon of the mighty: but in righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou iudge thy neighbour.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Lam. 4.9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
They that be ſlaine with the ſword are better then they that be ſlaine with hunger, for theſe pine away, ſtricken through for want of the fruits of the field.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving lately taken upon my ſelf that boldneſſe to ſpeake with you as you are one of the publique Iudges of the Kingdome, about an honeſt poor man that was unjuſtly and without any legall authority caſt into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and finding a very courteous, faire and rationall carriage from your Honour towards me at that time, imboldneth me the more at this time (being extraordinarily neceſſitated thereunto) to write a letter to you in my own behalfe. <hi>I</hi> being upon the fourteenth of April laſt arreſted at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> upon an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Treſpaſſe, by the Bayliffes thereof, at the ſuit of an unjuſt and troubleſome man,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115122:2"/>
commonly called <hi>Colonel Edward King;</hi> and the Bayliffes pretended it was for ſo many thouſand pounds (although <hi>I</hi> am confident that I never was ſix pence in his debt in my life) that they muſt have extraordinary Baile for my appearance.</p>
            <p>So that I was forced to give them two houſe-keepers in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and one ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, or elſe in their mercileſſe hands <hi>I</hi> muſt remaine, although <hi>I</hi> was very hard follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of my buſineſſe to perfection with the Parliament, which hath ſtuck there almoſt ſix yeares, to my extraordinary coſt, charge and loſſe of time, and although <hi>I</hi> am confident that it is as iuſt a cauſe as any is in the world, and hath ſo been adiudged by both Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament, as in this incloſed printed relation of the tryall and Iudgement of it before the Houſe of Lords the 13. of <hi>February.</hi> 1645. you may pleaſe to read.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> muſt ingenuouſly confeſſe that it did ſomewhat trouble me to be arreſted in that manner, having never before in my life been arreſted to my remembrance, and <hi>I</hi> was the more troubled in regard that my Ordinance of 2000 l. for my reparation, which lately paſſed in the Lords houſe, was depending in the houſe of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons. &amp; I was affraid that it might there ſtick, if <hi>I</hi> were diverted from following it, and <hi>I</hi> did not know but this arreſt might doe it, being of purpoſe for that end, as <hi>I</hi> have iuſt cauſe to believe.</p>
            <p>And being in a longing expectation for the Tearme, to ſee my <hi>Antagoniſts</hi> Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I found in it, that it is an Action of Treſpaſſe for 2000. l. pretending that I ſaid in <hi>October</hi> laſt, that Col. <hi>King</hi> was a Traytor, and I would prove him one and for ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away his good name which I ſcarce believe he ever had in his life, and conſidering with my ſelfe what to doe, I was reſolved to make a Plea at the Barr of the <hi>Common-Pleas</hi> (where you are the eldeſt, and chiefeſt Iudge) that Col. <hi>King</hi> and I, being both Soldiers, were in that condition to be governed by <hi>the Lawes martiall</hi> which were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with the ſtamp of Parliamentary <hi>Authority</hi> by the <hi>Generalls</hi> thereof: And he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving committed many grievous crimes againſt the Letter and true mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of them, I complained to the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> thereof, being both his Generall and mine; and at the ſame time, divers Gentlemen of the <hi>Committee of Lincolne,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Archer, &amp;c.</hi> having Articles of a very high nature againſt him, preſſed my Lord to a tryall of him at a <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> and at the very ſame time, the <hi>Major, Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Town-Cleark</hi> of <hi>Boſton,</hi> came to <hi>Lincoln</hi> to my Lord, with Articles of a ſuperlative nature againſt <hi>King</hi> their Governour, but could not get my Lord to let us injoy juſtice at a <hi>Councell of Warre,</hi> according to all our expectations, and as of right we ought to have had, which at preſent ſaved his head upon his ſhoulders, although he found cauſe to caſheere him of moſt or all his great and profitable commands.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding others endeavoured to try whether juſtice could be had againſt him in Parliament, and for that end, in <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1644. Mr. <hi>Muſſenden,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wolley</hi> and divers others of the Committee of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> did exhibit Articles of a very high nature to the Houſe of Commons againſt him, and to ſpeake their own words in their 4th. Article, they ſay.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That when he was laſt before <hi>Newarke,</hi> he ſent for a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine who kept <hi>Crowland.</hi>
               </q>
               <note n="†">Viz. Capt. <hi>Coney.</hi>
               </note> who obeyed his command, yet ſent word to him of the danger that that town was in, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſired his ſecond pleaſure, which was that he ſhould march who accordingly did, the Gentlemen of the Country, fearing the enemy procured Major <hi>Ireton</hi>
               <note n="†">N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Commiſſary Generall <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reton</hi> with Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax.</hi>
               </note> to ſend 100. Muſquetiers to keep <hi>Crowland,</hi> which he hearing of, took ill, that any without order from him ſhould come into his liberties, and commanded them to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115122:2"/>
be gone, who accordingly departed, the enemie preſently ſurprized the town, and thoſe few that he had left in it, by which meanes he betrayed the town unto the enemy, which was not regained without much charge, hazard, and loſſe<note n="†">Which blood I ſay lyes upon his head, and for which in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice he ought to be hanged.</note>
of many mens lives.</p>
            <p>And in the 12th. Article, they plainly accuſe him for betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Parliaments Garriſon of <hi>Grantham,</hi> theſe Articles with the reſt, having there hung ever ſince without a finall determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>King</hi> knowing that I was a maine witneſſe againſt him, in divers of the things laid to his charge, and bearing a malignant and inveterate mallice againſt me, for oppoſing him in his unjuſt and unwarrantable actions, (while I was his Major, and for diſcovering of them, and often complaining of him to the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and Lievt. Gen. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> &amp;c. to be revenged of me, did upon the 19th. day of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1645. plot, contrive, and by lying and falſe ſuggeſtions to ſome Members of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi>
               <note n="†">See Dr. <hi>Baſtwicks</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt me, pag. <hi>8.</hi> and my printed Epiſtle about that buſineſſe, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Iuly, <hi>25. 1645.</hi>
               </note> cauſed me to be committed as a priſoner, and as a priſoner, by vertue of that his uniuſt procurement, I lay till the 14 of <hi>October,</hi> 1645. to my extraordinary charge and dammage, yea, and to the hazzard of my life, as I could ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily, truly and undeniably demonſtrate, but at preſent read my booke called <hi>Innocency and truth iuſtified,</hi> pag. 29. 30. 31, 32.</p>
            <p>And yet neither he nor any man for him ever proſecuted any charge againſt me, for although I lay ſo long, yet was I delivered before ever <hi>I</hi> knew truly and legally where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I</hi> was impriſonned, as appeares by the following Coppy of my releaſement.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="writ_of_release">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Die Martis <hi>14</hi> October, <hi>1645.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>MR. <hi>Recorder</hi> acquainted the Houſe, that two Seſſions were now paſſed, ſince <hi>Liev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Colonel Lilburn</hi> was removed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and had continued a priſoner there, and that no information or other charge had been yet brought againſt him, and at this laſt Seſſions he humbly deſired either to be tryed or to be diſcharged, and it is thereupon reſolved upon the queſtion, that <hi>Liev. Col. Lilburne</hi> be forthwith diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from his impriſonment.</p>
                  <trailer>To the Keeper of <hi>Newgate or his Deputy.</hi>
                  </trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Hen. Elſing. Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And that <hi>King</hi> was the inſtrumentall cauſe of my impriſonment, appears clearly to me, by what I find recorded by his good friend, and my grand enemy Mr. <hi>Prinne,</hi> in the latter end of the 6th. pag. of his booke, intituled <hi>the Lyar Confounded,</hi> and by what I find recorded under <hi>Kings</hi> hand in the 8th. pag. of his co-partner, Dr. <hi>Baſtwicks</hi> book, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten againſt my ſelfe, for although Dr. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> be now my bitter Enemy, and his hand be with <hi>Kings</hi> to the information which Dr. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> there ſaith was put into the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> againſt me: yet I am apt to thinke that <hi>King</hi> was the Ring-leader in it, becauſe at that time there was no viſible nor profeſſed breach of friendſhip betwixt Dr. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> and my ſelfe:</p>
            <p>Vpon which provocation by <hi>King,</hi> it might be, and I doe believe it to be true, that I might be free in my diſcourſe at ſeverall times of <hi>King,</hi> and the forementioned charge of Treaſon given into the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> againſt him, and I am very confident it will be made good by ſufficient proofes and witneſſes, according to the rules of Warre, when it there comes to a tryall, but doe not own the words ſpecified by him in every particular.</p>
            <p>Therefore I conceive it uniuſt, irrationall, and Anti-Parliamentary, for an inferior
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115122:3"/>
and ſubordinate Court, <hi>as the Court of Common Pleas is</hi> to meddle with this buſineſſe, it being now dependent in Parliament, the ſupream Court, and unjudged there as yet, although the proſecutors are ready at their utmoſt perill to prove their charge againſt him.</p>
            <p>Therefore my Lord, in my apprehenſion, <hi>Kings</hi> former mallice manifeſted about my commitment, and his preſent bringing me before you, are meer evaſions and tricks to terrifie me and all others from proſecuting him in Parliament, and alſo (under favour) your medling with it in your Court, it being ſtill depending in Parliament, and not by them referred to you, is an incroachment upon their Priviledges, and I am the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmed in this opinion, when <hi>I</hi> ſeriouſly read over Mr. <hi>Prinnes</hi> Booke, cal'd <hi>the doom of Cowardice and Treacherie,,</hi> he being Colonel <hi>Kings</hi> very good friend and Councellor, and therefore his words in this caſe are of the more weight and authority <hi>Titus</hi> 1.12. being a profeſſed adverſary to me, who citing the Rolles of Parliament of the 1. <hi>R.</hi> 2. <hi>num.</hi> 38. 39. 40 in his 2, 3, 4, 5, 6 pages, which containes the caſe of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miny</hi> and <hi>Weſton,</hi> hath theſe obſervations and inferences from them, in the 7 page thereof:</p>
            <p>That it is to be remembred, that <hi>Jeffery Martin</hi> Clearke of the <hi>Crown</hi> made this very Record, and delivered it thus written in this preſent Roll, with his own hand, therefore ſaith he, from this memorable Record, I ſhall only obſerve theſe few parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That the ſurrender of Towns or Castles to the Enemy, through</hi> Cowardice <hi>or</hi> Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, <hi>is properly examinable and tryable only in Parliament.</hi> It being a detryment to the whole Kingdome, and ſo fit to be determined by the repreſentative Body of the Kingdome,</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That the</hi> Cowardly <hi>delivering up of any</hi> Town <hi>or</hi> Caſtle <hi>by the</hi> Governour <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to the Enemy, is a</hi> Capitall offence, <hi>deſerveth</hi> death, <hi>and likewiſe the loſſe of it through his negligence or default.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That every</hi> Governour, <hi>who takes upon him the custody of any</hi> Fort <hi>or</hi> Town, <hi>is obliged in point of</hi> Truſt, <hi>and</hi> duty under Paine of DEATH <hi>to defend it to the utmoſt extremity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That the concurrent conſent of a</hi> Councell <hi>of</hi> Warre <hi>or</hi> Soldiers, <hi>to render up a</hi> Town <hi>to the Enemie before utmost extremity, for the ſaving of the Houſes, Lives and Goods of the Soldiers or Inhabitants, is no juſtifie excuſe at all to exten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſuch a</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours <hi>diſhonourable Surrender and offence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That thoſe who are accuſed of ſuch an unworthy</hi> Surrender <hi>of any</hi> Town <hi>or Caſtle ought to be apprehended and kept in ſafe cuſtody, till</hi> their tryalls be paſt, <hi>and not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to goe at large.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That a</hi> Governour <hi>giving timely notice of the Enemies approach, of the weakneſſe of the</hi> Garriſon <hi>his ſuing for timely ſaid, and repulſing of the</hi> Enemie <hi>for a ſeaſon, will no wayes excuſe his ſurrender of a</hi> Town <hi>or</hi> Caſtle, <hi>unleſſe he bold it out to the utmoſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, or Surrender it by the conſent of thoſe, who intruſted him with the</hi> Cuſtody <hi>thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>That the violent Battery of the</hi> Walles, <hi>or drayning of the</hi> Dykes <hi>of any</hi> Caſtle <hi>or</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>or any breach made in them by the Enemy</hi> (though extraordinary powerfull) <hi>are no ſufficient cauſes or excuſes for any</hi> Governour <hi>to Surrender them upon compoſition to the Enemie, while there is ſufficient</hi> victualls, men <hi>or</hi> ammunition <hi>to defend them; And that they muſt in no wiſe be ſurrendred, without conſent of thoſe who put in the</hi> Governour <hi>till the greateſt part of the</hi> Soldiers <hi>be ſlaine, the</hi> victualls <hi>or</hi> ammunition <hi>quite ſpent, &amp; all hopes of reliefe diſpaired of utterly upon good grounds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115122:3"/>Which is cleare (ſaith he) by the caſe of <hi>Weſton,</hi> who made a better defence of the Caſtle of <hi>Outhrewick</hi> with 38. men onely, againſt more then 8000. Enemies, (who beſiedged, aſſaulted, battered it for 6. dayes together, with <hi>nine great Cannons and other Engines,</hi> and pleaded farre more in his defence of his ſurrender of it, then many now can doe, for ſurrendring of <hi>Townes and Caſtles</hi> of far greater importance, then this Caſtle was, <hi>and yet for all this</hi> Weſton <hi>in full Parliament was adjudged to death for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre the words of an adverſary to me, and <hi>Kings</hi> eſpeciall friend and councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, and therefore of the more weight and authority. <hi>Titus</hi> 1.12, 13.</p>
            <p>Therefore my Lord, laying all theſe things together, as 1. Col. <hi>King</hi> and I being both Soldiers under one Generall, <hi>namely the</hi> Earl of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> who was authorized by <hi>Parliament</hi> to govern his Army by <hi>Martiall Law,</hi> which <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aw</hi> was plainly printed by the ſame Authority, and openly publiſhed to the view of every Commander, Officer and Soldiers, for tranſgreſſing againſt which Articles, many in a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rciall way have loſt their lives, and no other viſible Rule that <hi>I</hi> knew off, was to be the Rule and Iudge of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> actions, or offences, but that <hi>Law,</hi> unto the power and authority of which, both Col. <hi>King</hi> and my ſelfe did voluntarily ſtoop, and therefore (as I humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) we are not to be tryed by the Rules of the <hi>Common Law</hi> (which I thinke no man in the world fully and truly knowes) for our actions commited in our Soldier condition, which is the true cauſe betwixt him and me. 2. I did my duty according to the truſt repoſed in me, <hi>by the State legall and repreſentative,</hi> and by my Generall from whom I had my commiſſion, and according to the private command of Lievtenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> which was to be faithfull in my place, and to complain, either of Col. <hi>King,</hi> or whomſoever I groundedly knew, did any actions that tended to the ruine of <hi>Salus Populi,</hi> the ſafety of the People, or the State univerſall, and he promiſed me upon his honour and Reputation,<note n="*">Both at Sleford and elſewhere.</note> that he would doe the beſt he could to have juſtice done, which is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he very life of all ſocieties or Common wealths, and that without which the people cannot be happie or ſafe; yea, and he gave me the reaſon, wherefore he ſo earneſtly tyed me to it, which was becauſe our Generall with his Army was to march out of <hi>Lincoln ſhi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and that country being lately wonne out of the hands of the Cavaliers, there being very few of that Country it that time that deſired Command under the Generall, (therefore ſaith he) we are neceſſitated to make uſe of Col. <hi>King,</hi> and to make him governour of <hi>Boſton</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> upon whom he look'd then as an active popular man, who promiſed to doe mighty things for the good of that Country, and the publique.</p>
            <p>But in regard divers of the cheife men of <hi>Boſton</hi> doe miſlike him, I have therfore <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> in his behalfe engaged my ſelfe to them for him, <hi>that he ſhall be faithfull, juſt and honeſt towards them,</hi> and therefore in regard I have no large experience of the man, and of his temper, I principally looke upon thee <hi>Lilburne</hi> and thy Lievte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Colonell, <hi>John Bury by name,</hi> whoſe faithfulneſſe I can reſt upon, and for both of whom I have uſed my intereſt, to place on purpoſe with him, <hi>that ſo if hee ſhould break out to the diſhonour of my ingagement, and the detriment of the publique,</hi> I may from time to time bee ſure to know of it from you that ſo it may be prevented before it be paſt remedy.</p>
            <p>But <hi>King,</hi> being puffed up with his command, tooke upon him an abſolute, regall tyrannicall authority over all his Officers, but eſpecially thoſe that were betruſted in Commiſſion aſwell as himſelfe, <hi>and to doe his cheife actions by the rule of his owne will without their privytie or advice, ſomething like divers of the preſent Grandees in the Army
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115122:4"/>
who by their late actions declare they have forgot their ſolemne agreement made at Newmarket,</hi> which tended to the ruine of al that were under him, &amp; conſequently of that whole country, he haveing treacherouſly loſt <hi>Crowland, and Boſton</hi> put in extream danger, by his abſolute wilfulneſſe, <hi>if not treachery,</hi> the making known whereof, with his carriages at <hi>Newarke Seige</hi> &amp;c. coſt me in ſending poſts to the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and Leivtenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> then, in or about <hi>Camebridge,</hi> I am very confident, 20. or 30. l. which ſo madded him, that he impriſoned Major <hi>Rogers</hi> for daring to goe and complain againſt him. <hi>I</hi> being in thoſe ſtraights in regard of the charge I had taken upon me, I durſt not ſtir my ſelfe, till all was cleare, without feare or danger of an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, he having already by the Law <hi>of his owne Will</hi> caſhiered his Leivtenant Colonell without ground or cauſe, and endeavoured the appa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent deſtruction of Capt <hi>Camebridge</hi> and all the honeſt, zealous, and conſcientious men, under his command, <hi>which to me was an ill Omen of his intentions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore I ſay, ſo ſoone as I durſt leave my charge, I poſted away to <hi>Bedford,</hi> where I found my Generall, and Leivtenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and told them both fully of <hi>Kings</hi> carriage, and that he commanded his forces to march forward and backward, where, and when he pleaſed, without the advice, aprobation and conſent of his Field Officers &amp;c. who were to ingage their lives a thouſand times more then himſelfe, in managing the deſignes he ſet them about, and that the Committee of <hi>Lincolnſheire had paid him divers thouſands of pounds, to pay his Officers and Souldiers</hi> at <hi>Newarke</hi> Seidge, but I could not heare that he paid one penny to any Officer there, and for my own part I am ſure I could not get a penny from him, (yet lying baſe Mr. <hi>Prynn</hi> in one of his late bookes lyingly chargeth me with being accountable to the State for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 2000.l. received of him ſee my anſwer to his charge in the laſt end of my booke called <hi>The reſolved mans reſolution,</hi>) although I am confident I tooke as much paines both night and day, and hazarded my perſon as freely, and as often as any Major at that Leaguer did.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe, although the Country ſent in great ſtore of proviſion for his Regiment gratis, yet he and his under Sutlers, made both my ſelfe and others of his Officers and Souldiers, pay ready money for a great part of it, to their extraordinary diſcontent, provoking them thereby to mutiny And ſo full was be of arrogancy pride and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (conteſting with al, or moſt of the cheife Commanders there) that Sir <hi>Iohn Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drum</hi> told me, that he kindled ſuch a fire of contention amongſt them that he durſt ſcarce cal a <hi>Councel of Warre</hi> to conſult how to manage their buyſines, being there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually in conteſtation with my Lord <hi>Willoughby,</hi> Col, <hi>Roſſiter,</hi> Sir <hi>Myles Hubbard,</hi> Sir, <hi>Iohn Paragraffe</hi> and divers of the <hi>Lincoln</hi> Committtee &amp;c. which did ſo trouble and diſtract the old Knight Sir <hi>Iohn Meldrum,</hi> our Commander in cheife, that he knew not wel what to do, when Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> came upon us, by reaſon of our own diſtactions among our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And I dare confidently averre it upon my conſcience, that hee <hi>(namely King)</hi> was one of the greateſt inſtruments of our overthrow and ruine, and therefore if <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> (Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> in the 2. page of the foreſaid booke recordeth (<hi>was proclaimed a Traytor, by the whole Army in the</hi> 12. <hi>yeare of King Edward the ſecond; for departing in diſcontent from the Army, at the Siege of Barwick, by meanes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it was not taken, and the Seige raiſed, then I deſire to know what Colonell King</hi> deſerveth, who at the Seige of <hi>Newark</hi> carried himſelfe ſo, that hee did raiſe diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, and litle better then mutinies, by meanes whereof the ſiege was not only raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but the whole Army in a manner deſtroyed, to the extraordinay danger of the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115122:4"/>I alſo told my Lord that after the articles of agreement was concluded, Colonell <hi>King</hi> commanded (and in a manner forced me) contrary to the agreement, to march away his <hi>Regiment</hi> in a hoſtill manner, with their armes, &amp;c. by meanes of which we were ſet upon by their horſe, and forcibly diſarmed, which did alſo occaſion the plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of us, as violaters of our Covenant and contract; to the diſparagement of the whole Army, yea, and the Parliament it ſelfe, and to the extream hazard and danger of abundance of our lives; yet <hi>King</hi> was ſo honeſt, and valiant, that as ſoone as he ſaw the ſtorme fall upon us, he fairly left us, and ſhifted for himſelfe, without being plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as wee were<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at which bout I loſt well nigh a 100 l. being plundred from the crowne of my head to the ſole of my foote, and forced over hedge and ditch in by wayes for the ſafety of my life to march almoſt ten myles without a hat, or Perewig (having by cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſickneſſe lately loſt my heire in <hi>Oxford</hi> Priſon) britches, or doublet, bootes, or ſhooes.</p>
            <p>I further told him, that the Towne of <hi>Boſton</hi> had been in extreame danger, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Lincolne</hi> was diſcerted, and <hi>Ruperts</hi> forces poſſeſſed of it, and daily newes brought into <hi>Boſton,</hi> that <hi>Rupert</hi> would aſſault it on both ſides the river; I moved Colonell <hi>King,</hi> that ſeeing the armes of his owne Regiment &amp;c. was loſt, and he in no poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to defend the Towne of himſelfe at the preſent, that therefore (the Towne being of that conſequence, that if it ſhould be loſt, the Enemy might preſently make it, the abſoluteſt ſtrong Towne in <hi>England</hi> for themſelves) that he would forthwith ſend to Colonell <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alton,</hi> then Governour of <hi>Linne,</hi> to intreat him to lend him at his great need and ſtrait<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, or 500 men to defend the Towne, till ſuch time that he could get his owne Regi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> againe together which he abſolutely refuſed, and told me plainly that hee would never ſend for another to command and affront him in his owne Juriſdiction, which the <hi>Linne</hi> men would doe, (he ſaid) if they come, at which I being exceedingly troubled, that he ſhould preferre his owne domination before the preſervation of ſo conſiderable a Towne and Gariſon, it made me beleeve hee in intended to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray it, which I told to Captaine <hi>Camebridge,</hi> now in Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Army.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I went to Mr. Major, then as I remember, at Alderman <hi>Tilſons,</hi> and told them both, with ſome others, that their Towne was in extraordinary danger to be loſt and they all undone, if they did not looke about them preſently, and told them all the diſcourſe I had had with their unjuſt oppreſſing Governour, and told them I conceived all was not right, and therefore I judged my ſelf bound in duty and conſcience both before God and man, to tell them what I apprehended of things, and how neare their danger and ruine was at hand, and if they would not helpe to ſave themſelves according to the Law of Nature, their ruine be upon themſelves; they deſiring of me to let them know, what I would adviſe them to, I told them my adviſe was<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for as many of them to goe with me to Colonell <hi>King</hi> once againe, as they thought fit, and let us joyntly preſſe him to ſend to <hi>Linne</hi> for men, and if he would not doe it, that then we might doe it without him.</p>
            <p>Vpon which, we went, and at firſt found him obſtinate till (as I remember) <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman Tilſon</hi> told him that if he would not Joyne with them, they would write to the Governour without him) upon which he was drawne to ſubſcribe, but my Lord of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> and the Governour of <hi>Lyne,</hi> or ſome others in authority; being mindfull of us in our ſtraites, had ordred Col <hi>Waltons</hi> Major, Major <hi>Franckling,</hi> a ſtout and gallant man, with about 400. men, to come by ſea to us, &amp; as I remember, his orders were, that he ſhould ſecure <hi>Boſton;</hi> upon the arival of whom, Col. <hi>King</hi> immediately commanded
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115122:5"/>
them out of the Town, to go and beſiedge <hi>Crowland</hi> which a little before by treachery of his own abſolute wilfull negligence, he had given up unto the declared Traytors and profeſſed enemies of the ſtate and Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Of which as ſoone as I fully underſtood, I went to Major <hi>Frankling,</hi> and deſired to ſee his Order by vertue of which he came to <hi>Boſton,</hi> and told him how things ſtood with us, and in what temper I conceived my Colonell to be, and therefore entreated him to be ſenſible of the truſt repoſed in him, and of his owne Honour, and reputation, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing unto him that if he at the command of Col. <hi>King</hi> marched away with al his men conſidering his orders, &amp; the condition w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Town was in, I ſhould look upon it as a meere deſign betwixt him and Col <hi>King</hi> to betray the Town indeed, telling him how weak and unfortified the Town was in a manner all round about, being in divers places eaſy for a man with a Pike ſtaffe to leape over it, and therefore there was no way in the eye of reaſon to preſerve it, ſeing the Enemies intention (as we heard) was to fal upon it, unleſſe his men ſtayed in it, or at leaſt the major part of them.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he went to Col. <hi>King,</hi> and (as I remember) in Alderman <hi>Tilſons</hi> Hill, debated with him his poſitive command, and with much adoe prevailed that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and a great part of his Souldiers ſhould ſtay to defend the Town, and my ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left by Col. <hi>King,</hi> with the conſent of the Major and Aldermen, to take care of the towne I went to Major <hi>Frankling,</hi> and deſired him to go with me to Collonell <hi>King,</hi> to know what Amunition he had in his Magazine, who aſſured us upon his reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that he had a hundred barrels of powder, and all things fitting beſides, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bid us take no care for Amunition, and being very buſie in ſending away men, Guns &amp;c, to the intended leaguer of <hi>Crowland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did not go to the Magazine, to ſee whether he had told us truth or no, he having taken a quantity of powder with him, and another ſent him, he ſends his war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to the Magazine keeper, for ten barrels more, not ſignifying one word of his minde to me, who was then be truſted with the Towne, upon the receipt of which old Mr. <hi>Coney</hi> the Magazine keeper, came and told me that he had received an order from the Collonell, to ſend him ten barrels of powder, and ſaith he what ſhall I doe, for there is but ten barrels in all in the Magazine:</p>
            <p>At the hearing of which I ſtood amazed, and told him it could not be poſſible, for (ſaid I) ſuch a day I went to the Colonell with Major <hi>Frankling,</hi> and he did aſſure us that he had 100 barrels in ſtore, but Mr. <hi>Coney</hi> aſſured me that there was not one more then 10. the which if we ſend to him, there is none to keep their guards (ſaith he) I asked him, if there were not a private ſtore houſe for powder, and he told me none at all, then we began to reckon how many barrels were gone out, ſince he aſſured Maior <hi>Frankling</hi> and my ſelfe that he had a 100. in ſtore, and all that both the Magazine Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and my ſelfe could reckon, with thoſe 10. in his hands, and all he had ſince that day delivered out, was, as I remember, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4 or 26.</p>
            <p>Whereupon I went to Alderman <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſons,</hi> and asked him whether the Maior, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and the reſt of his brethren, had not a private Magazine, and he told me no, but asked me wherefore I demanded ſuch a queſtion of him, whereupon <hi>I</hi> told him all the ſtory, at which he ſtood amazed, and from him I went to Col. <hi>Kings</hi> wife, and deſired to know of of her, whether ſhe knew of any private Magazine of powder that her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band had, and ſhe told me no.</p>
            <p>Then I told her all the buſineſſe, and ſaid to her, that I wondered her Husband ſhould aſſure Maior <hi>Frankl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng</hi> and my ſelfe, that he had 100. barrels of powder, when he had but 28. and that he ſhould ſend for all that he had left out of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115122:5"/>
aſſuring her that if the ten barrels he had ſent for<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſhould be ſent him, we ſhould not have one left in the Magazine to defend the Towne with, being then in expectation of the Enemy to aſſault us, I told her for my part I could not pick out the Engliſh of it; which I deſired the Earle of Mancheſter ſeriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſider of, who ſeemed then to be very much affected with it.</p>
            <p>And I being by the Generall ſent poſt to <hi>London</hi> to the Committee of both Kingdomes about his marching to take <hi>Lincolne</hi> againe, and from thence to march to <hi>Yorke;</hi> to joyne with the <hi>Scots;</hi> I in the third place ceaſed not to put that (which lay upon me as a duty) forwards, as ſoon as an opportunity ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and renewed my complaint aga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſt him at <hi>Lincolne,</hi> and deſired it might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a faire hearing before the Generall and a Counſell of Warre, and Mr, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> and others of the Committee of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> drew up a very hainous charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>King,</hi> and laboured hard for a tryall; and in the third place, the Major and Aldermen, and Town Clerke of <hi>Boſton,</hi> came to <hi>Lincolne</hi> with their Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles againſt him, which were home enough, and to my knowledge preſſed Leiu. Generall <hi>Crumwell,</hi> to uſe all his intereſt in my Lord, that they might be admitted to make them good, before him, and a Counſell of Warre, but wee could not all prevaile, the reaſon of which I am not able to render, unleſſe it were, that his two Chaplins, <hi>Lee,</hi> and <hi>Garter,</hi> prevailed with the Earles two <hi>Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lins, Me Aſh,</hi> and <hi>Good, to caſt</hi> a <hi>Scotch-clergy miſt over their Lords eyes,</hi> that he ſhould not be able to ſee any deformity in Colonell <hi>King,</hi> but this I dare confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ently ſay, if there we had, had faire play, and juſtice impertially, <hi>King had as ſurely dyed, as ever Malifactor in England did;</hi> and to uſe the words once again of his own boſome friend, and Counſeller, Mr. <hi>Prinne</hi> in page the 6 of the fore cited book, <q>If the late Baron of <hi>Grayſtock</hi> who was a Lord, and one of the Peares of the Realme, and had taken upon him ſafety to keep to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Granfather (King of <hi>England</hi>) the Town of <hi>Barwick:</hi> The ſaid <hi>Barron</hi> perceiving afterward, that the ſaid Granfather, addreſſed himſelfe to ride into <hi>France,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Barron</hi> (without command of the ſaid Granfather) committed the ſaid <hi>Barwick</hi> to a valiant Eſquire <hi>Robert Deogle,</hi> a Leiv. to the ſaid <hi>Barron,</hi> for to keep ſafe the own of <hi>Barwic</hi> to the ſaid Grandfather, and the ſaid went as an horſe man to the ſaid parts of <hi>France,</hi> to the ſaid Granfather, and there remained in his company. During which time an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault of war, was made upon the ſaid Town of <hi>Barwick,</hi> by the ſaid <hi>Scots,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Robert,</hi> as Leiv. to the ſaid <hi>Barron,</hi> valiently defended the ſame, and at laſt by ſuch forceable aſſaults, the ſaid Town was taken upon the ſaid <hi>Robert,</hi> and two of the ſons of the ſaid <hi>Robert</hi> ſlain in the defence of the ſame, notwithſtanding that the ſaid <hi>Barron</hi> himſelfe, had taken upon him the ſafeguard of the ſaid Town, to the ſaid Granfather, and departed without command of the ſaid Granfather, and the ſaid Town of <hi>Barwick</hi> loſt, in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115122:6"/>
abſence of the ſaid <hi>Barron,</hi> he being in the company of the ſaid Granfather, in the parts of <hi>France,</hi> as aforeſaid, It was adjudged in Parliament, before his Peares, that the ſaid Town was loſt in default of the ſaid <hi>Barron,</hi> and for this cauſe he had judgement of life and member, and that he ſhould forfeit all that he had.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay if this Lord, deſerved to dye who left a deputy ſo manfully to defend the Town &amp; alſo was himſelf with the King in the ſervice, much more C. <hi>King</hi> meerly in reference to <hi>Crowland</hi> ſingly, who being Governer thereof, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving placed Captain <hi>Cony</hi> therein as his Deputy, with a company of men, ſent for him in a bravado humour to <hi>Newarke,</hi> when he had no urgent neceſſity for him, unleſſe it were that the world might ſee the bravery of his Regiment, which by his argumentation amounted to about 1400, when Cap. <hi>Cony</hi> certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied him, that the Towne being generally Malignant, &amp;c. would be in great danger by the <hi>Beaverkers</hi> of being loſt if he ſhould come away, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>King</hi> ſent to him againe, and did command him away, and put in a guard of ſlender and unſafe men, which preſaged a loſſe of it to the Committee reſiding in <hi>Holland,</hi> upon which they acquainted Commiſſary Generall <hi>Ireton,</hi> then Deputy Governour of the Ile of <hi>Ely,</hi> and earneſtly intreated him to ſend a ſtrong guard to preſerve and keepe it, and he accordingly ſent (as I remember) Captain <hi>Vnderwood,</hi> a ſtout man, with about 100. Souldiers &amp;c. of which when <hi>King</hi> heard, he was exceeding mad, and did write a moſt imperious bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Letter, (yet as I beleeve in the hands of Commiſſary Generall <hi>Ireton</hi>) to command them out of his juriſdiction whereupon they were neceſſitated to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and leave <hi>Crowland</hi> to his own ſlender and treacherous guard, by meanes of which, within a little while after the Enemy had advantage to ſurprize that Town without oppoſition, or difficulty, and did it, <q>So that to ſpeake in the words of the Articles remaining in Parliament againſt him, he betrayed that Town, which was not regained without much hazzard and loſſe the expence of a great deale of treaſure, and many mens lives;</q> the blood of all which lies upon his head, for the loſſe of which alone (beſides his treachery both to the State univerſall and repreſentative) he ought to dye without mercy, by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and undiſpenſable Law of God, made long before that ever the Jewes were a Nation, or had any cerimoniall Law given unto them, which law is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.5, 6 where God ſpaking to <hi>Noah</hi> and his ſons, ſaith thus, <hi>And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly your blood of your lives will</hi> I <hi>require: at the hand of every beaſt will</hi> I <hi>require it, and at the hand of every man: and at the hand of every mans brother will</hi> I <hi>require the life of man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood, by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, for in the Image of God made he man,</hi> reade <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.10. But <hi>King,</hi> though his own hands did not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Souldiers that loſt their lives in taking it in againe, yet he was the true fountain and cauſe wherefore their blood was ſhed, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.8. <hi>Judg.</hi> 9.24.2.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115122:6"/>
               <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.9. having apparently, by his wilfulneſſe and treachery, loſt the Town; and therefore wilfull blood being upon his head, he ought to make a legall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and expiation by his own blood: I wiſh with all my ſoule the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament (your Lordſhip, and all the reſt of the Judges of this Kingdome) would ſeriouſly conſider and ponder upon this unrepealable law of God, that ſo wilfull <hi>murderers</hi> and <hi>blood-thirſty men</hi> might not eſcape the hands of Juſtice; and ſo bring wrath from God upon the whole Kingdom, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.10, 11.12. <hi>Deu.</hi> 19.10. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.38. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7 5, 6. and 19.3, 4. <hi>Lament.</hi> 4.13, 14. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. <hi>Joel</hi> 3 19. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.8. which cannot be expiated but by the blood of him that ſhed it, <hi>Num.</hi> 35.33. <hi>Deu.</hi> 19.12, 13. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.11, 12. 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.5, 6.31.32, 33. and 21.19. and 22, 34, 35.37, 38. and 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 9.7, 8, 9, 10 26.33.36.37. and <hi>char.</hi> 24.2.3, 4. but eſpecially that you would <hi>thinke upon the grand murtherers of England</hi> (for by this imperciall Law of God there is no exemption of <hi>Kings, Princes, Dukes, Earles, Barrons, Judges, Parliament men,</hi> or <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> more then of <hi>Fiſher-men, Coblers, Tinkers,</hi> and Chimney-<hi>Sweepers</hi>) upon whoſe ſhoulders all the innocent blood that hath in ſuch abundance been ſhed in this Kingdome, &amp;c. lyes, for which reckoning I am ſure the ſcore is not acquitted in the accompt of God, nor ought it not to be in the account of man, <hi>For if the innocent and righteouſneſſe of one Abel, cryed ſo loud for vengance in the eares of God, againſt Cain, that God curſed him and all he went about, Gen.</hi> 4.9, 10, 11. How much more will the blood of thouſands, and ten thouſands of innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that hath been lately ſhed in <hi>England,</hi> cry loud in the eares of God, for wrath and vengance againſt thoſe that have been the true fountain and cauſe of it, for ſhed it is, and upon ſombody the guilt of it lyes; and therefore it is but a folly and madneſſe, for the <hi>King, Parliament,</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> to talke of peace, till inquiſition be made for <hi>Englands</hi> innocent blood, and Juſtice done upon the guilty, and wilfull ſheders of it, for beſides the Law of God in <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. he ſaith plainly, <hi>Numb.</hi> 35.31. <q>That there ſhall be no ſatisfaction taken for the life of a murtherer, but that he ſhall ſurely be put to death, and in verſe 33.</q> God declares that the ſhedding innocent blood defileth and polluteth a land, and that, that cannot be cleanſed of the blood that is ſhed therein, but by the blood of him that ſhed it, and for the innocent blood that <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> ſhed in <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> (although a King) God ſent bands of the Caldeans, Syrians, Moabites, and Ammonites to deſtroy <hi>Iudah,</hi> and remove them out of his ſight, for the ſinnes of <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> their King, and for the innocent blood that he had ſhed, (which the text ſaith) The Lord would not pardon, 2 Kings 24.2, 3, 4. Yea, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Saul</hi> (though a King) ſlew ſome of the Gebonites contrary to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant made with them, <q>God ſent a famine upon all Iſrael for three yeares, for that very innocent blood ſhed by the King, and there was no expiation or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to be made therefore, but by the blood of him that had ſhed it;</q>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115122:7"/>
and therefore becauſe he himſelfe was dead and his blood could not be had, <q>ſeven of his ſons (of his own blood) muſt and was hanged up to make ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction:</q> therefore 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1, 2, 3, 4. to the 9</p>
            <p>My L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fferable provocation of Collonell <hi>King,</hi> forceth me to preſent theſe lines unto you, and I doubt not, but theſe will tend to his long deſerved ruine; and therefore to ſpeake in the words of his friend Mr. <hi>Prine,</hi> "in a caſe of the like nature; it is the juſt hand of God, many times ſo farr to dementate the very wiſeſt polititians" as to make themſelves the principall contrivers of their own infamy and ruine: for his Knavery, lying in a hole as it were, now he hath by his "arreſting me, and bringing me before your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip (who I conceive have nothing to doe with the buſineſſe, <hi>being it is depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in Parliament the ſupream Court of the Kingdome</hi>) neceſſitated me to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the whole ſtate of the buſineſſe betwixt him and me to the view of the world, becauſe at your <hi>Barre</hi> I cannot make plea at large to the whole body of the Articles, but muſt be tyed up,<note n="*">And although <hi>King</hi> be guilty of Treaſon accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Ordinance of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament &amp; by Articles of war eſtabliſhed by them, yet according to Law, cannot be ſaid to be guilty of Treaſon for violating of them.</note> as I am told, to a ſingle plea, that is to ſay, to <q>plead either guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or not guilty,</q> unto which I cannot without ſnares yeeld unto, beſides I muſt, as I am told, plead at your Barre by <hi>Serjeons</hi> at Law, none of which I know, and therefore will not truſt them, come ruine and deſtruction, and what ever will of me, Againe, my Lord, I muſt there be tryed by a Jury that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowes me, nor I them, nor knowes any of <hi>Kings</hi> habituated knavery, nor unerſtands any thing of Martiall Law, <q>the only rule to try him and me in this caſe, and that which is worſt of all, they are cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen (as I am told) by the under Sheriffe, of which kinde of creatures I never heard any great commendations of their honeſty, but have heard of much jugling and packing betwixt them and ſuch kind of crafty and large conſcion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fellowes, as my Adverſary <hi>King</hi> the Lawyer is.</q> Againe, my Lord that which is the greateſt miſchief of all, &amp; <hi>the opreſſing bondage of England</hi> ever ſince the <hi>Norman yoke</hi> is this, I muſt be tryed before you by a Law <hi>(called the common Law)</hi> that I know not, nor I think no man elſe, neither doe I know where to find it or read it, and how I can in ſuch a caſe be puniſhed by it, I know not: For, my Lord, I have been with divers <hi>Lawyers</hi> about this very buſineſſe, and I cannot find two of them of one mind, or that can plainly deſcrib unto me what is the way of your goings, ſo that I profeſſe I am in the darke amongs briers and thornes, <hi>and faſt in the trap by the heeles,</hi> and enemies round about me ready to deſtroy me, if I be not very wary with my tongue, and which way to get out, or how, or to whom to call to for help I know not, <q>for ſuch an unfathoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble gulfe have <hi>I</hi> by a little ſearch found, the Law practices in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115122:7"/>
to be, that ſeriouſly I think there is neither end nor bottom of them,</q>
ſo many uncertainties, formalities, puntillo's, and that which is worſe, <q>all the entryes and proceedings in <hi>Latine,</hi> a language <hi>I</hi> underſtand not,</q> nor one of a thouſand of my native country men, ſo that my Lord, when I read the Scripture, and the Houſe of Commons late <q>unparaleld Declaration, it makes me think that the practiſes in the Courts at Weſtminſter Hall flow not from God nor his Law, nor the law of Nature and reaſon, no nor yet from the underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of any righteous, juſt, or honeſt men, but from the Devill, and the will of Tyrants, and oppreſſors.</q> for,</p>
            <p>
               <q>Firſt my Lord, the Houſe of Commons declaration <hi>April</hi> 17. 1646. tels me, that their inventions are not to change the antient frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſafty &amp; weal of the people, a moſt Goulden ſaying)</q> but J am ſure it cannot be i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the peoples ſafety, nor wealfare, to have their lives, liberties, and eſtates, judged by a "Law, the entrings and proceedings of which are in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, and ſo without their underſtanding the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r caſes in <hi>Heathen Greeke</hi> or <hi>Ped<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers French,</hi> and ſo beyond their knowledge, <q>and many of their rules in the orracle of Judges breſts, whoſe judgements many times have been deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the lives liberties and eſtates, of all the free men of England, witneſſe there late Judgement in ſhipmoney &amp;c. neither are ſuch practizes agreeable to the Antient conſtitutions of the Kingdome.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And ſecondly when God gives his Law unto the ſonnes of men, he doth it plainly, without <hi>ambiguous termes,</hi> and in their own <hi>language,</hi> as firſt for <hi>Adam,</hi> the law God give him was plaine and ſhort, with a declared penalty annexed unto, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2 16.17. <q>and the Lord God commanded the man, ſaying, of every tree of the Garden thou mayeſt freely eat. But of the tree of the knowledge of good and evill, thou ſhalt not eat of it, for in the day thou eateſt thereof, thou ſhalt ſurely die.</q> And his law in the 9. of Gen. about murther is as plaine as this, <q>for who ſo ſhedeth mans blood (ſaith he) by man ſhall his blood be ſhed, for in the Image of God made he man; and ſo likewiſe when God comes to give a law unto the Iſralites as a nation, (yea; and that law which we call the <hi>Morrall law,</hi> and obſerve as binding to us to this day.)</q> 
               <q>he doth it in plaine words, without ambiguous or doubtfull tearmes, ſhort and in their own tongue <bibl>
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 20.</bibl>
               </q> and that the people might be at a certaintie, Moſes as his Miniſter, and officer, writ, <q>and read it in the audience of the people, unto which they gave their conſent, <bibl>Exo. 24.3, 4.7.</bibl>
               </q> and after that God writ them himſelfe with his finger, and delivered them to Moſes, that ſo the people might be taught them, <hi>Exo</hi> 24.21. &amp; 31 &amp; chap. 34. yea, and in this <hi>plaineſſe,</hi> was the Law; God gave unto them, which he did not only barely make, and ſo let the people goe ſeeke them where they could find them, <q>but he alſo with Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, proclaimes them openly and as if that were not enough, that ſo they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115122:8"/>
might know the Law, and not in the leaſt plead ignorance of it, <hi>Moſes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares it to them againe, and againe, <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. and chap. 6. &amp; chap. 9. &amp; 11.</bibl>
               </q> 
               <q>Yea and commands them to teach their Children, and to ſpeak of them, when they ſit in their houſe, and when they go abroad, and when they lye down and riſe up, yea and that they ſhould write them upon the poſts of their houſes, and upon their gates, <hi>Deut.</hi> 11.19.20. yea and that they ſhould write them very plaine, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.8 and the reaſon is becauſe the juſt God hath done, and will doe juſt and righteous things, and will not be ſo unjuſt as to puniſh men for tranſgreſſing a law they know not, and therefore ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the behalfe of the juſt God, and his law, Its not hidden from thee, neither is it far off, it is not in heaven, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay who ſhall goe up for us to heaven, and bring it unto us that we may heare it, and and do it; neither is it beyond the Sea, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay, who ſhall goe over the Sea for us, and bring it unto us, that we may heare it, and doe it, but the word is very nigh unto thee, in thy mouth, and in thy heart that thou mayſt do it, (ſo ſaith he) I have ſet before thee this day life &amp; good, death and evill, <bibl>
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.11, 12, 13, 14.19.</bibl>
               </q> yea and that the generations to come, might not thinke that God dealt hardly with them, in exacting obedience from them, who lived not in <hi>Moſes</hi> dayes to heare the Law ſo ſolemnly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, he delivers as a ſtanding Law (in future generations) unto the Prieſts, Elders, and people, that at the end of every ſeaven yeares, in the ſolemnity of the yeare of releaſe, in the feaſt of Tabernacles: When all <hi>Iſrael</hi> is come to appeare before the Lord thy God, in the place which he ſhall chooſe: Thou ſhalt read this Law before all <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their hearing. Gather the people toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, men and women, and children, and thy ſtranger that is within thy gates, that they may heare, and that they learne, and feare the Lord your God, and obſerve to doe all the words of this law: And that their Children which have not known any thing, may heare and learne to feare the Lord your God, as long as you live, <hi>Deut.</hi> 31.9, 10.11, 12.13. So we ſee how juſt and exact God is to the people, in giving them a ſhort, plain and eaſie to be underſtood Law, in their own tongue, and not in the language of ſtrangers and what care he takes to have it publiſhed and taught unto the people, before he requires obedience to it, or puniſheth them for violation of it.</p>
            <p>But if we will but impartially read our Engliſh hiſtories, we ſhall clearely find, that the tedious, unknown, and impoſſible to be underſtood, common law practiſes in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> came in by the will of a Tyrant, namely <hi>William</hi> the Conquerer, who by his ſword conquered this Kingdome, and profeſſed he had it from none but God and his ſword <hi>Daniel</hi> fo. 42. who ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued their honeſt and juſt law (<hi>Speed</hi> fol. 424) commonly called the law of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the Confeſſor, and as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith, fol. 44 ſet up new tearmes, new con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, new formes of pleas, new offices, and Courts, and that whereas ſaith
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115122:8"/>
he fol. 46. before the cauſes of the kingdome were determined in every Shire, and by the Law of King <hi>Edward ſe.</hi> all matters in queſtion ſhould upon eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all penalty, without further deferment, be finally decided in their <hi>Gemote</hi> or <q>conventions held monethly in every hundred, he ordained, that foure times in the yeare for certain dayes, the ſame buſineſſe ſhould be determined in ſuch places as he would appoint, where he conſtituted Judges to attend for that purpoſe, and others from whom, as from the boſome of the Prince, all litigators ſhould have juſtice, and from whom was no appeale, and made his Judges (ſaith <hi>Martin</hi> in his hiſtory fol. 5.) follow his Court upon all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moves, which tyred out the Engliſh Nation, with extraordinary troubles, and exceſſive charges in the proſecution of their ſuiths in Law, and ſaith he fol. 4, he alſo enacted, and eſtabliſhed ſtrait and ſevere Lawes, and publiſhed them in his own language<note n="*">Which was French.</note> (as all the practices of the Law, and all petitions and buſineſſe of the Court were) by means whereof many (who were of great eſtate, and of much worth) through ignorance did tranſgreſſe, and their ſmalleſt offences, were great enough to intitle the Conqueror to the land, and riches which they did poſſeſſe: all which he ſeized on and took from them without remorſe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And although the agrieved Lords, and ſad people of <hi>England,</hi> humbly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titioned him, that according to his oath (twice formerly taken) that he would reſtore them the Lawes of St <hi>Edward,</hi> under which they were born and bred, and not add unto all the reſt of their miſerie, to deliver them up to be judged by a ſtrange Law they underſtood not, whoſe importunity ſo farre prevailed with him, that he took his oath the third time, to preſerve their Lawes, and liberties, but like a <hi>perjured Tyrant,</hi> never obſerved any of his oaths, and the ſame (ſaith <hi>Daniel</hi> fol. 43. did <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, and King <hi>John,</hi> &amp;c. and yet notwithſtanding there followed (ſaith he) a great innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both in the Lawes and Government of <hi>England,</hi> ſo that this ſeems rather to be done to acquit the People, with the ſhow of the continuation of their ancient Cuſtomes and Liberties, then that they enjoyed them in effect. For the little conformitie between them of former times and theſe that followed upon this change of State, and though there may be ſome veines iſſuing from former originalls, yet the maine ſtream of our Common law, with the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice thereof, flowed out of <hi>Normandy,</hi> notwithſtanding all objections can be made to the contrary, and therefore J ſay it came from the Will of a Tyrant and an Oppreſſor.</p>
            <p>But it may be objected that the law it ſelfe, is not now either in <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Latine,</hi> and therefore not ſo bad as you would make it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall anſwer in the words of <hi>Daniel,</hi> fol. 251. That it is true, upon the Petition of the Commons to <hi>Edward</hi> the third, he cauſed pleas which before
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115122:9"/>
were in French, to be made in Engliſh, that the Subjects might underſtand the Law by which he holds what he hath, and is to know what he doth, a bleſſed act, and worthy ſo great a King; if he could thereby have rendred the ſame alſo perſpicuous, it had been a worke of eternall honour, but ſuch (ſaith he) it is the late of Law, that in wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> language ſoever it ſpeakes, it never ſpeaks pain but is wrapt up in ſuch difficu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties and myſteries, as all profeſſions or proficate) as it gives more affliction to the people, then it doth remedy, and therefore when <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> after many bloody Battle, and the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of many hundred thouſand of Pounds, was obtained and confirmed by <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt, in the 25 yeare of his raign, divers Patrons of their Country, as Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> in his Proem before the ſecond part of his <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtitutes,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares, that after the making of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> &amp;c. divers learned men in the Lawes (that I may uſe the words of the Record) kept Schooles of the Law in the City of <hi>London</hi> and taught ſuch as reſorted to them, the Lawes of the Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taking their foundation from <hi>Magna Charta and Charta de Forreſta,</hi> which King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond ſought to impeach, and therefore in the 19. yeare of his Raign, by his Writ, commanded the Major and Sheriffes of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> to ſuppreſſe all ſuch Schooles, under great penalties, (ſuch enemies are oppreſſors to the peoples knowledge and underſtanding of their lawes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, that ſo they may rule by their wills and pleaſures, for the impugning and infringing of which &amp;c this wicked and leud King was diſthroned, at the doing of which, he confeſſed, that he had been miſguided, and done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things wherof now (too late) he repented, which if he were to governe againe he would become a new man and was moſt ſorrowfull to have offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the State, as it ſhould thus utterly reject him, but yet gave them thankes that they were ſo gracious unto him, as to eldeſt his elde ſonne for King, <hi>Speed fol.</hi> 666.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Henry</hi> the third, in the 38, yeare of his Raign confirmed the great Charter. which notwithſtanding he continually broke them, and fetcht over the <hi>Poictonians</hi> by the advice of his evill Councell, to over awe his people, and anniholate their liberties, wherefore his Nobles, &amp;c. ſent him expreſſe word, that unleſſe he would amend his doings, they would expell him and his evill Councellors out of the land, and dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for the creation of a new King, <hi>Daniel, Fol.</hi> 154</p>
            <p>But I deſire not to be miſunderſtood, for in the harſhneſſe of my expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the Common law, I put (as I conceive) a cleare diſtinction of it, from the Statute law, which though there be many faults in it, as I could eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew, yet I deſire not here to ſay any greater evill of it, then that the 14 28, 29 Chap. of <hi>Magna Charta, the Petition of Right, and the late act for aboliſhing the Star-Chamber,</hi> are gallant lawes, and the beſt I can find in the whole vol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminous
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115122:9"/>
booke of Statutes, but in my apprehenſion, they fall farre ſhort, in a ſufficiently providing for that which lately the Honourable houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſaith is the end of all Government, the ſafety and weale of the people, for in my judgement, they doe not poſſitively and legally hold out a ſufficient ſecurity to hedge about, to keep in peace, and to preſerve the ſplendor, and glory of that underived Majeſtie and King-ſhip, that inherently reſides in the People, or the ſtate univerſall, (the repreſentation or derivation of which, is formally and legally in the ſtate Elector repreſentative and none elſe, (whoſe actions ought all to tend to that end) againſt incroachments, uſurpations, and violence of all its creatures, officers and Miniſters, in the number of which are Kings and Dukes themſelves, from whom and for whom they have all their power and authority, as the executions of their will and mind, for their good and benefit, and to whom they are accountable for the faithfull diſcharge of that truſt repoſed in them, as not only Scripture, but nature and reaſon, doth fully prove, yea, and our owne writers, eſpecially the late Obſervator, and Mr. <hi>Prynn,</hi> in his <hi>Soverain power of Parliaments and Kingdomes,</hi> printed by ſpeciall authority from the Houſe of Commons, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 2. 1643.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Although <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> be commonly called the Engliſh mans inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, becauſe it is the beſt in that kind he hath, and which was purchaſed with ſo much brave Engliſh bloud, and money, by our fore fathers, before they could wring it out of the hands of their tiranicall Kings, <hi>(ſucceſſors of William the Conquerer)</hi> as I have largely elſewhere clearly manifeſted, yet alas in my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehention, it falls ſhort of <hi>Edward the confeſſours</hi> Lawes, which the Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rob'd England of, and in ſtead of them, ſet up the dictates of his own will, whoſe <hi>Norman</hi> rules, and pactizes to this day yet remaines in the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Common Law</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> by reaſon of their tediouſneſſe ambiguities, unceartainties, the entryes in Lattine (<hi>as bad as</hi> the French) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is not our own tongue, their forcing men to plead by Lawyers, and not permitting themſelves to plead their own cauſes, their compelling of perſons to come from all places of the Kingdome, to ſeeke for juſtice at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> which is ſuch an iron <hi>Norman</hi> Yoke, with fangs and teeth in it, that if we were free in every particular elſe, that our hearts can think of, yet were we ſlaves by this alone, the burthen of which ſingly, will pirce and gall our ſhouldiers, and make us bow and ſtoop to the ground, ready to be made a prey, not only by great men, but even by every cunning ſharking knave, and therefore it is no wonder that Mr. <hi>Glyn</hi> the preſent Recorder of <hi>London,</hi> and the reſt of his jangling contentious tribe of Lawyers in the Houſe of Commons, were lately ſuch bitter enimies againſt the great Petition of the honeſt plaine Citizens of London (which Petition you may read in my printed Epiſtle of the 31. <hi>May</hi> 1647. to Col. Hen. <hi>Martin</hi> pag. 29, 31, 32, 33 34, 35.) as they were, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115122:10"/>
nothing would ſerve their turnes but to have it burnt by the hands of the hang-man, ſeeing it honeſtly deſires the remedie of the aforeſaid grand evils, which if it ſhould be, downe goes the Lawyers wicked trade, which principally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in ſetting the people together by the eares each with other, whoſe jangling deviding practizes are as ſutable to the peace of a well governed Common-wealth, as Gunpouder and Brimſtone is to quench a fire.</p>
            <p>O therefore that your Lordſhip would deſire and ſolicite our honourable Parliament according to the late Declaration forever to anihilate this Norman innovation and reduce us back to that part of the antient frame of government in this Kingdomes before the Conquerers dayes, and that we may have all cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and differences decided in the County, or Hundred, where they are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or do ariſe, without any appeale but to a Parliament, and that they may monthly be judged by twelve men, free of &amp; honeſt condition choſen by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, with their grave or chief Officer amongſt themſelves, &amp; that they may be tyed by a pennall law without oaths to judge every mans cauſe aright, without Feare, Favour, or affection, and then farewell jangling Lawyers, the wild-fire, deſtroyers, and bane of all juſt, rationall, and right governed Common-wealths; and for faciliating of this worke, and the prevention of fraud, I ſhall only make uſe of Mr. <hi>Iohn Cooks</hi> words a Lawyer of Grayes Inn, in the 66. pag of his late publiſhed book called a vindication of the Profeſſors, and profeſſion of the Law, where he preſcribes a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ready remedy againſt frauds, which is that there might be a publique Office in every County: to regiſter all Leaſes made for any lands, and all bonds and Contracts of any value, for (ſaith he) it is a hard matter to find out all Recognizances. Judgements, extents, and other charges, and two chargeable for the Subject, that for 12. d. or ſome ſuch ſmall matter, might know in whom the intereſt of land remaines, and what incumbrances lye upon it, and every eſtate or charge not entred, there to be void in law, and that the country have the chuſing of the Regiſters in their reſpective Counties once a yeare, upon a fixed day, and that they have plaine rules and limitations, made by the authority of Parliament, and ſevere penalty inacted for the tranſgreſſing them, which penaltie is the only way to keep them in awe, and to doe impartiall juſtice and right.</p>
            <p>My Lord, I hope you will not be offended at me for my plainneſſe, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if you conſider the neceſſities laid upon me, for I profeſſe really, I am not able to imagine any other remedy for my preſervation but this, having had my Petition about this buſineſſe, above a moneth in divers of my friends hands in the Houſe of Commons, but cannot get it read.</p>
            <p>And having conteſted above this 7. yeares, with all ſorts and kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that would deſtroy me, and having often been in the field, among Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets and Swords to maintaine the common liberties and freedomes of <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115122:10"/>
againſt al the declared trayterly oppugners therof, and having by the goodnes of, God eſcaped many dangers and deaths, and being in my own apprehenſion ready to be ruinated and deſtroyed, by a weapon inferior to a Taylors Bod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, (namely) a Formallitie, or Puntillo in the Law, it hath rouzed up my ſpirit, to charge it with a Soldiers pure reſolution, in a new and unwonted manner, being neceſſitated to caſt all care behind me, and ſay unto my ſelfe, that as hetherto I have not lived by any mans favour and grace, ſo, for my own ſafety, I will now be afraid of no mans indignation or diſpleaſure, coſt what it will, and if I periſh, I periſh, down right honeſty and plaine dealing being to me the beſt pollicie, knowing that uprightneſſe begits boldneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If your Lordſhip, or any other great man, be moved with choller or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt me, (as I deſire you may not) and ſhall, endeavour to doe me a miſchiefe, for this my plain dealing, I hope I ſhall be kept out of danger by the authoritie of the Parliaments own Declaration, but eſpecially by thoſe words of theirs, in their exhortation to men to take their Covenant, which are thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as for thoſe</hi> Clergy men. <hi>who pretend, that they (above all others) cannot Covenant to extirpate</hi> Epiſcopall Government, <hi>becauſe they have (as they ſay) taken a ſolemn oath to obey the Biſhops.</hi> in licitis &amp; honeſtis, <hi>they can tell and if they pleaſe, that they that have ſworne obedience to the Law of the Land, are not thereby prohibited from endeavouring by all lawfull meanes the abolition of thoſe</hi> Lawes, <hi>when they proue inconvenient or miſchievous &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I am confident, that if I fall in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the hands of thoſe that made the Covenant, (who are the fitteſt interpreters of it) I ſhall doe well enough; But from the Sect of the <hi>Adamites</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Alderman Adams was then Lord Major, and a chiefe promoter of the Cityes damnable and wicked Remonſtrance.</note> that would have no man live in <hi>England</hi> that are honeſter then themſelves, and from the late <hi>London Remonſtrance</hi> that would have all men diſfranchiſed (although never ſo honeſt) that are not of their minds and judgements, and who doe and would rob the <hi>repreſentative body of all the Commons of England, of their Legiſlative power,</hi> and from the executi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ners of ſtrange and unknown Lawes, which deſtroy and undoe men, (though never ſo upright) by forma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lities and puntillo's, <hi>good Lord d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liver</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my houſe in Halfe-moon Alley in Petty-France, neer Biſhops Gate</hi> London <date>June 6. 1646.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips Servant, and a true bred Engliſhman, <hi>John Lilburne.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>The forementioned Petition thus followes,</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115122:11"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the Repreſentive Body of the Commons of England: Jn Parliament aſſembled. The humble Petition of <hi>Liev. Col. Iohn Lilburne.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
            <p>THat upon the difference betwixt the King, and Parliament, the <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> for the defence and preſervation of their lawes and juſt liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by authority of Parliament were neceſſitated to take up Armes, for the ſuppreſſion of the jorces raiſed by the King. In this warre againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Forces raiſed in the <hi>Eaſterne Aſſocitation,</hi> were committed and intruſted under the command of the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi>
               <note n="*">Who was ſince impea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of Treaſon, by <hi>L. G.</hi> C. for being falſe to his truſt, and had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly loſt his head therefore, if <hi>L. G.</hi> C. had followed it as he ſhould.</note> as Major Generall there, from whom your Petitioner had a Commiſſion to be Major to Col. <hi>King,</hi> and particular inſtructions and private di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, from Lievt. Gen. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> to take and give unto them, or one of them, (upon all occaſions) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and intelligence, of the ſtate and condition of <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> under the command of the ſaid Col <hi>King,</hi> and of the carriage and behaviour of the ſaid Col. <hi>King,</hi> towards the Country and Solderie, and how he diſcharged his place and truſt. Which your petitioner with all faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe and diligence did accordingly, to his extraordinary expences, not neglecting any advantage or opportunity, which might further the publique ſervice, or diſcover the deſignes of the enemy, or the ſaid Col. <hi>Kings</hi> miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and neglect of his truſt and duty the ſaid Col <hi>King</hi> taking upon him an unlimitted and unwarantable power <hi>deſtructive to the truſt repoſed in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That upon your Petitioners diſcoverie and making known both unto the Exarle and Liev. Gen, <hi>Cromwell,</hi> (according to his inſtruſtion and truſt repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in him) the malignancy, inſolencies, and unfaithfullneſſe of the ſaid Col. <hi>King,</hi> to the Sate, in the neglect of his charge, and his bad uſage of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, to the great diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſervice of the Parliament, and danger of the loſſe loſſe of the whole country, <hi>(Crowland being by him betrayed unto the enemie)</hi> and was not regained without great charge and hazzard, yea and the loſſe of many mens lives, the ſaid Col. <hi>King</hi> was there upon diſcharged, and put out of all his commands and offices, (being then very many<note n="*">Viz. Col. of Horſe, C. of Dragoons, C. of Foot, Governour of Boſton and the parts of Holland, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the City of Lincolne and the county thereof. Beſides he had a power in himſelfe to le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie money, which hee did at his pleaſure, and diſpoſed of it at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to whom he pleaſed.</note> and profitable) but was not brought to tryall for his ſaid offences, at a Councell of Warre, which your Petitioner and others much endeavoured to have done. Whereupon Mr. <hi>Muſſenden.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wolley,</hi> and divers others (Gentlemen of quallity) of the Committee of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1644. exhibited to this Honourable Houſe, ſeverall
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115122:11"/>
Articles, (ſince printed) a Coppy whereof is hereunto annexed, againſt the ſaid Col. <hi>King,</hi> thereby charging him with ſeverall Treaſons, Inſolencies, ſetting up and exerciſing an Arbitrary, exorbitant, and unlimitted power, over the country and Souldiery, with many other inſolencies, and foule miſdemeanors, all which are yet depending before this Honourable houſe, and not yet deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, being ſome of them, for or concerning the loſſe and ſurrender of Towns to the enemie, through his treacherie or negligence, and ſo the offence Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall, and properly examinable, and only tryable in Parliament, as appeares <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 1. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>Num.</hi> 38 39.40. <hi>Rot. Parl.</hi> 7. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>Numb.</hi> 17.22.</p>
            <p>Now the ſaid Col. <hi>King,</hi> being privie to his own guiltineſſe, and well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Petitioner to be a principall witneſſe for the proof of divers of the ſaid Articles, out of his mallice and wickedneſſe to your Petitioner, upon a ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe complaint, and untrue ſurmiſes, made by him to this Honourable Houſe, in <hi>Iuly</hi> laſt, procured your petitioner by Vote of this Houſe to be committed to the cuſtody of the Serjant at arms attending this honourable houſ<note n="*">Se before Pag. 5.</note> your Petitioner being thence removed to <hi>Newgate,</hi> but he, nor any other never proſecuted any charge againſt him, and after he had laid about 13. weekes there, he was diſcharged of his impriſonment by order of thio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſe<note n="*">See my printed Letter of the 25. Iuly, 1645. and Innocency and truth juſtified, p. 31. 32 33. 34.</note> &amp; knows not to this very day wherfore he was committed.</p>
            <p>And the ſaid Col. <hi>King,</hi> the more to vex and unjuſtly trouble your Petitioner and to the end to take away his teſtimony, and deter others from appearing againſt the ſaid Col. <hi>King,</hi> upon his tryall upon the ſaid Articles, a little before <hi>Eaſter Tearme</hi> laſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cauſed your Petitioner to be arreſted at his own ſuite, upon an action of 2000. l. for pretended words aleadging by his Declaration, That your Petitioner ſhould have ſaid that the ſaid Col. <hi>King</hi> was a trayter, and he gives forth in ſpeeches, he will undoubtedly recover the ſame againſt your Petitioner, and thereby utterly ruine him, and is indeed very likely to doe the ſame, by theſe his ſiniſter practizes, if by this Honourable Houſe, your Petitioner be not relieved and protected, according to juſtice and equity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Your Petitioner therefore humbly deſires this Honourable Houſe Will be pleaſed, in regard your Petitioner hath not done or ſaid any thing againſt the ſaid Col.</hi> King <hi>but what will be proved when he ſhall be brought to</hi> Tryall <hi>before this honourable Houſe upon the ſaid</hi> Articles <hi>and</hi> Charge; (<hi>and for that your Petitioner cannot at</hi> Law <hi>give any</hi> Plea <hi>in</hi> Bar, <hi>or juſtification of the words pretended to be ſpoken by him, untill the ſaid Col.</hi> King <hi>be either convicted or acquitted vpon his</hi> Tryall, <hi>upon the ſaid Articles and charge) to give</hi> Order, <hi>and</hi> direction <hi>to the ſaid Col</hi> King, <hi>and to the</hi> Iuſtices <hi>of the Court of</hi> Common Pleas, (<hi>where the</hi> Action dependeth) <hi>to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, and no further proceed upon the ſaid</hi> Action <hi>of</hi> 2000<hi>l. againſt your Petitioner. And for the good and ſatisfaction of the Kingdome, and the freeing and vindication of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115122:12"/>
your Petitioners integrity and faithfulneſſe in what he hath ſaid or done touching the premiſes, to bring the ſaid Col.</hi> King <hi>to tryall</hi> (in a Parliamentary way) <hi>that ſo he may receive c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> puniſhment for the injuries and wrongs he hath done, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he is charged in the ſaid Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> Lilburne.</signed>
               <hi>And your Petitioner ſhall pray, &amp;c.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <head>Articles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xhibitted agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt Col. <hi>Edward King,</hi> for his inſolencies and miſdemenors in the County of <hi>Lin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oln,</hi> to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Honourable Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> in <hi>Auguſt 1644.</hi> by Mr. <hi>Muſſenden,</hi> Mr. <hi>W Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and diver wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re of the Committee of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimis,</hi> that to the great diſcouragement of the County, he doth openly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, his ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ghting of mens good aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction to the Parliaments ſervice, by expreſſing that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieth not that men ſhould doe the Parliament ſervice voluntarily, but that he would by his power force them to ſerve.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That he doth pay thoſe great ſummes of money raiſed by him out of the County, only to whom he pleaſeth, againſt all equity and juſtice, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Lord of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der to the contrary,</p>
            <p n="3">3 That he hath publickly declared his ſlighting the Ordinances of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and done very many tiranicall and arbitrary actions, by impriſoning divers perſons at his pleaſure, and exacting great ſummes of money, at ſuch time when neceſſity could be no plea, with many other particulars,</p>
            <p n="4">4 When he was before <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wark</hi> he ſent for a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain<note n="*">viz. Captaine Cony.</note> who kept <hi>Crowland,</hi> who obeyed his command, yet ſent word to him of the danger that town was in, and therefore d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſired his ſecond pleaſure, which was that he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould march who accordingly did the Gentlemen of the Country fearing the enemie, procured Major <hi>Ireton</hi>
               <note n="*">Now Commiſſary Ireton.</note> to ſend a 100 Muſquetiers to keep <hi>Crowland,</hi> which he hearing of took ill that without order from him any ſhould come into his liberties, and commanded them to be gone, who accordingly departed, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie preſently ſurprized the towne, and thoſe few that he had left in it, by which meanes he betrayed the town unto the enemy, which was not regain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed without much charge, hazard, and loſſe of many mens lives.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That he gives protections for ſecuring both perſon and goods, to thoſe who are profeſſed enemies to the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That he imployeth ſuch Officers as, are altogether unfit for the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes ſervice.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That he doth moſt groſly and unworthily affront and abuſe the wel-affected Gentry of the Country,</p>
            <p n="8">8. That he doth encourage deſperate Malignants, and animateth them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wel-affected,</p>
            <p n="9">9. That he and his officers have impriſoned men, wel-affected to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iament and cauſed their houſes, cheſts, trunks, &amp;c. to be ſearched for pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115122:12"/>
braſſe, and linning, and threatened that they would make it coſt one of them his whole eſtate, and that one of his officers would not take three hun-pounds for his own ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That at the ſiedg before <hi>Newark</hi> ſuch proviſion as the Country had volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily and freely ſent in to Col. <hi>Kings</hi> quarters at <hi>Winthrop,</hi> for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the ſouldiers, his officers would not deliver without money, although they had not pay, to the extreame oppreſſion and diſcouragement of the Country.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That he ſent three warrants to Cap <hi>Buſhy</hi> at <hi>Tatterſhall,</hi> to take away a great quantety of wool which was bought by Mr. <hi>Rawſon</hi> one of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, and paid for with his own money, and ſo the ſaid <hi>Rawſon</hi> is likely to loſe his eſtate, although he hath been a ſufferer both for Church and com-wealth this twenty years, and hath made him a malignant, both in his words and letters, as much as in him did lye.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That when the enemie took Grantham, they being beaten from one part of the town, wheeled about to fall upon the other ſide, at a place cal'd the Spittlegate, which <hi>Major Savil</hi> being then Major of the towne percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, commanded Col. <hi>King,</hi> being then Capr. of a Company there to march with his Company to defend that place, Col. <hi>King</hi> anſwered, that he ſcorned to be commanded by him, and rather then he would be commanded by him, he would take his company and let the enemie into the towne, and he delayed ſo long before he would goe, that the enemy was entred at the ſaid port, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he came thither, by which meanes he betrayed that town.</p>
            <p n="13">13, That when Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſary <hi>James</hi> had brought in certaine ſheep from a malignant for the reliefe of the ſiedge at <hi>Newark,</hi> being then in great want, Col. <hi>King</hi> cauſed the ſaid ſheep to be reſtored to the malignant, and told the Commiſary, that he deſerved to be hanged, with divers other threatening reviling ſpeeches, notwithſtanding he had order from Sir <hi>Iohn Meldrum</hi> and the Committee for the taking of them.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That Col. <hi>King</hi> having promiſed the Lord of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> to raiſe a great number of Horſe and Foot the ſaid Col. <hi>King,</hi> as did appeare, not knowing how to raiſe ſo great a number, did to the great diſcouragement of the Country, take this courſe, in the firſt place he caſhiered Major <hi>Syler,</hi> &amp; with him three hundred Volentiers, which ſerved on their own charge, who with the towneſmen had alwayes defended the town of <hi>Boſton,</hi> that he might preſſe them to ſerve under him for pay; And ſecondly, he did ſieze upon, and detaine, four or five of the foot Companies belonging to the Lord <hi>Willough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> and did caſhiere ſome of the Captaines, becauſe they refuſed to forſake my Lord and to ſerve under him.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That the troopes of Colonel <hi>Cromwel,</hi> which were loſt at <hi>Coleby</hi> and <hi>Waddington</hi> were treacherouſly or ignorantly betrayed by Colonel <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115122:13"/>16. That to the great diſcouragment of the Country, he doth oppoſe and quarrell, with ſuch as have been moſt ſerviceable to the Country, and ſuch in whom the power of Religion is moſt eminent (viz) L. G. <hi>Cromwel,</hi> Mr. <hi>Ram</hi> and others, and that he impriſoned divers other very Godly men, and that for exerciſing the very power of Godlines, which he did in a very ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vile manner, and ſtill continueth an utter enemie to ſuch men as namely L. C. <hi>Berry,</hi> Major <hi>Lilburne,</hi> Capt. <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="17">17. That to the great diſcontent and diſcouragement of the Country, he and his Officers did quarell with, and flight the Committee at Lincoln, which was ſetled by ordinance of Parl who were men of the beſt eſtates, quality and integrity, and ſuch as were eſpecially commanded to ſerve the Country, and publickly vilifying them and their actions, and aſſuming their power without any authority.</p>
            <p n="18">18 That before this war began, he was an open and publck perſecuter and ſcoffer of religious men.</p>
            <p n="19">19 That he is a man of a turbulant and factious ſpirit, of meane condition and eſtate for ſo abſolute a command, that he hath received vaſt ſumes of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, amounting to about 20000l. much of which he hath levied in an illegal and obſcure way, and iſſued out accordingly, for which it is deſired he may give a ſpeedy accompt, and likewiſe of the reſt of his actions.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That in a factious and ſeditious manner, he did imploy ſome Agents to deliver blue ribbonds to ſuch as would ſtand for him, and ſhow themſelves his friends, to the great terrour, and diſcontent of the Country, and the harzard of raiſing a dangerous mutinie.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That he kept about 20. men to wait on him, whom he cald his life guard, to whom he gave extraordinary pay though they were exempted from all dutie, except it were to wait upon him &amp; advance his reputation and awe and affright the Country.</p>
            <p n="22">22. That he did awe and gaine the Country wholy after him, and that he might with better colour domineere, falſly ſtyling himſelfe Lievtenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall of the County of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To his much honoured friends the Councell of Adjutators.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honoured and faithfull Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving this day received a meſſage, by Lievtenant <hi>Chillington,</hi> and one more as comming from your ſelves, to deſire me ſafely to ſtate my cauſe to you, that ſo too morrow at the grand Councell of the Army, you might be able cleerly to expreſſe your reſults about it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to the Parliament upon it. In briefe the caſe is thus, after my deliverance out of <hi>Oxford</hi> Caſtle, I was made Major by Lievt. Gen. <hi>Crumw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll</hi> means to Col. <hi>Edward King,</hi> in <hi>Lincolneſhire,</hi> who ſeverall wayes betrayed his truſt, and did divers ſuch actions, that he deſerved, by the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of warre and Ordinance of Parliament, to looſe his life: of which <hi>I</hi> according to my du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the truſt repoſed in me, complained to my then Generall the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and Lievt. Gen. <hi>Crumwell,</hi> and with indefatigable paines for divers moneths together, ſpent good ſtore of my own money about it, but could not from the hands of my then Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115122:13"/>
obtaine one dram of effective juſtice upon Col. <hi>King,</hi> ſaying the loſe of his great and many commands, although the Committee of <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> and the Magiſtrates of <hi>Boſton,</hi> and Lievt. G. <hi>Crumwell</hi> were all proſecutors as well as my ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e.</p>
            <p>Whereupon in <hi>August</hi> 1644 Mr. <hi>Muſſenden</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wolley,</hi> and divers of the Committee of Lincolne preferred a formall impeachment of high treaſon according to Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the rules of Warre, to the Houſe of Commons containing 22. Articles againſt the aforeſaid Col <hi>Edward King,</hi> which they cauſed to be printed, and which <hi>I</hi> reprinted at the latter end of my Epiſtle to Iudge <hi>Reeves,</hi> da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted <hi>Iune</hi> 6. 1646 in the 4. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. Articles of which they poſſitively accuſe him, <hi>for traiterouſly betraying Crowland, and Grantham into the hands of the Cavieleers, then profeſſed enemies (in Armes) to the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment,</hi> and my ſelfe being an active proſecuter of <hi>King,</hi> to bring him to a tryall in the Houſe of Commons, upon the ſaid impeachment, by way of revenge, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates with D. <hi>Baſtwick</hi> then bitter againſt me, for my conſtant activitie againſt the perſecuting Presbyterian Government, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the 12 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1645. joyntly with him ſends<note n="a">Which ſaid lying and falſe paper, you may read in the <hi>8.</hi> p. of <hi>Baſtwicks</hi> moſt abuſive printed de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence againſt me, of the <hi>9.</hi> of Auguſt, <hi>1645.</hi> and in the <hi>6.</hi> page of Pryns baſe and lying book called the Lyar confounded.</note> in unto the Speaker or ſome other of the Houſe of Commons, a moſt lying falſe malicious paper, under their hands againſt Col. <hi>Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton, Mr. Haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lins</hi> and my ſelfe, about 60000. l. that then was ſaid to be ſent to <hi>Oxford</hi> by the Speaker, information of which was that day in the morning given into a Committee of the houſe of Commons, by 3. Citiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns of London, viz Mr. <hi>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tty, Mr. Rawſon, and Mr. Worly,</hi> whereupon about 8. or 9 a clock at night by the Speakers means in the Houſe of Commons, contrary to all equitie, law, juſtice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>thout either knowing my accuſer or accuſation, or ſo much as being called into their Houſe, though then at their doore, to ſpeake one word for my ſelfe, voted by the Houſe into the cuſtody of the Serjeant at Armes,<note n="b">Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch Order you may read in the <hi>13</hi> pag. of my anſwer to <hi>Pryn,</hi> called Jnnocency and truth ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, dated in Decemb. <hi>1645.</hi>
               </note> and as priſoner without any more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe I remained with his man <hi>Knight</hi> till the 9. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1645 at which time corrupt Mr. <hi>Lawrence Whittaker,</hi> and the reſt of the Committee of Examination, moſt illegally contrary to all law, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted me to <hi>Newgate</hi> priſon, for refuſing to anſwer to their unjuſt Interrogatories concerning my ſelfe,<note n="c">Which illegall order you may alſo read in the <hi>17.</hi> pag of the aforeſaid In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noceny, &amp;c.</note> and my foreſaid malicious enemies by their powerfull intereſt, prevailed with the houſe of Commons upon the 26. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1645. to make an expreſſe Order to try me at <hi>Newgate</hi> Seſſions,<note n="d">Which mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cious order you may likewiſe read in the <hi>30.</hi> pag of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Innocency and Truth juſtified.</note> before Mr. <hi>Glyn</hi> Recorder of London, my profeſſed enemy, and who as <hi>I</hi> was told had threatned my utter diſtruction, and in all likelyhood I had hanged for it, if God had not inabled me fully and effectually to have ſtaited my caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th my pen, which <hi>I</hi> preſented in print to the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld<note n="e">And which by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of <hi>Englands</hi> Birth-right is reprinted at the beginning of that not able book.</note> and my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ury, before they paſſed upon me, which as I was told gave them ſuch ample ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, that they would not meddle with me, and ſo by ſpec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l order of the Houſe of Commons, of the 14. of <hi>October</hi> 1645. <hi>I</hi> was freely diſcharged<note n="f">Which diſcharge you ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> read in the <hi>35.</hi> pag. of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency and truth juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> without being ever charged by any man all that time, legally with the leaſt crime in the world, the whole ſtory of my then unjuſt uſage you may fully read in my book called Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and truth juſtified, being ignorant to this very houre of the true or declared cauſe wherefore I was ſo committed and toſſed and tumbled by the Houſe of Commons, ſaving but for what I find in <hi>Baſtwicks</hi> and <hi>Pryns</hi> abuſive books, mentioned before in the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. And being at liberty, <hi>I</hi> followed my Star-Chamber buſineſſe, then depending in the Houſe of Commons, and with much adoe, as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115122:14"/>
you may read in the 67 72. pages of Innocency and truth juſtified got it from thence tranſmitted to the Lords, before whoſe bar, upon the 13. of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1645. I had with my councell Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Iohn Cook,</hi> a fair and juſt hearing, upon which they made an effectuall and legall Decree,<note n="g">Which Decree you may read in the latter end of my relation of my Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells plea before the Lords the <hi>13.</hi> Feb. <hi>1645.</hi>
               </note> for the deſtroying and annihillating of that moſt illegall and bloody ſentence paſt againſt me in the Star-Chamber in Anno. 1637. and within a few dayes after decreed me 2000. l. for my dammages or reparations, and tranſmitted an Ordinance down to the houſe of Commons, for inabling me to receive the money, in which Houſe that Ordinance hath laid do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ever ſince.</p>
            <p>But Col <hi>King</hi> knowing I was the chiefeſt man he was in danger of, judged himſelfe not ſafe, nor long lived, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that money, which would enable me with vigour and ſtrength to proſecute him, which he kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough I would doe, therfore to divert me, and to be revenged of me, he moſt maliciouſly and cauſeleſly upon the 14. of <hi>April</hi> 1646. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the juſt priveledge of Parliament, and the common law of<note n="h">See Vox Plebis, pag. <hi>23 24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>England,</hi> cauſed me at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> as <hi>I</hi> was following my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, then depending before the Houſe, by whom I ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in juſtice to have been protected againſt him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by the Bayliffe thereof, to be arreſted into the court of common Pleas, in an action<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or treſpaſſe for 2000. l. pretending that I in <hi>October</hi> before had ſaid, Col <hi>King</hi> was a Traytor, and I would prove him one, whereupon I clapt in my petition to the Houſe of Commons, to deſire them to appoint a time according to juſtice and reaſon, for the bringing the ſaid Col. <hi>King</hi> to a tryall in a Parliamentary way upon the ſaid impeachment depending before them being ready thereupon to juſtifie any thing I had ſaid of the ſaid <hi>King,</hi> deſiring according to reaſon, equity and juſtice, they by order would ſuſpend the determination of the ſaid <hi>Kings</hi> acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of 2000. l. in the Common Pleas, till in a Parliamentary way he was upon his ſaid impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either condemned, or juſtified, and I improved, all the intereſt I had in the world, both in Lievt. Gen. <hi>Crumwell,</hi> then (ſitting in the Houſe,) and all the reſt of my friends I had there, but could not ſo much as get it read, a reaſonable anſwer of which<note n="i">Which Petition is printed at the latter end of my Epiſtle to Iudge <hi>Reeves,</hi> which you may read in the <hi>20. 21.</hi> pag. of the <hi>2.</hi> Edition of it, foregoing this relation.</note> had kept of all my preſent ſorrowes, and down to <hi>Oxford</hi> Leager with L. G. <hi>Crumwell</hi> J went, to ſee, if with C <hi>Ireton</hi> and other of my friends there, I could do any thing to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave of a tryall at Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon law, till the tryall in Parliament was over, but my journey was to no purpoſe ſaving vexation to my ſelfe ſo left in the ſuds by L. G. <hi>Crumwell,</hi> who firſt ingaged me in it, and promiſed to ſtand to me. So up to <hi>London I</hi> came, and to variety of Councell I went, from all of whom I did underſtand, that by the ſtrength of the Common law I muſt put in no other Plea, then either guilty or not guilty, and likewiſe that the Common Law tooke no notice of Ordinances or Articles of War, nor of any thing called treaſon, but what was done againſt the King: by which argument Col. <hi>King,</hi> in the betraying of <hi>Grantham</hi> and <hi>Crowland</hi> to the Kings party, had done that which was juſtifiable and not puniſhable, which was more then I knew before, ſo that in this extraordinary tranſcendent ſtrait to ſave my ſelf from being condemned by a Iudge, whoſe power flows meerly from an Ordinance of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in 2000. l. for no other crime, but for the faithful endeavouring to diſcharge my duty to the Parliament, in endavouring the puniſhment of one profeſſedly under the Parliaments juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction for violating &amp; tranſgreſſing their Ordinances, unto which he himſelf ſtooped &amp; ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>I</hi> was of neceſſitie forced and conſtrained when all other juſt and rationall wayes and meanes failed me, to pen my plea my ſelfe, and in print direct it to the Iudge, and called it the juſt mans juſtification, now with the whole relation of my preſent ſuffering in the hands of Mr. <hi>Saxby.</hi> In the pening of which <hi>I</hi> was neceſſitated to touch upon the Earle of <hi>Mancheſters</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, unjuſt and unworthy dealings with me.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115122:14"/>And the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> being my profeſſed and implacable enemy, (who formerly would have hanged me for being over quick in taking <hi>Thickell</hi> Caſtle) for my ſo deeply ingaging with <hi>L.G. Crumwell,</hi> in his charge of treaſon and breach of truſt, given into the Houſe of Commons againſt he ſaid long <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce deſerving, to be beheaded Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> and for which I am ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e injuſtice, long ſince fully deſerved to looſe his head,<note n="a" place="bottom">For a Member yet ſitting in the Houſe of Commons, with in a day or two after Mr. <hi>Lile</hi> made the report of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his examination of that buſineſſe to the houſe, told me that in his judgement, the charge againſt <hi>Strafford,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mely, was but a toy to it, and not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quarter ſo punctually and fully proved.</note> took the advantage (being then ſpeaker of the Houſe of Peers) to revenge himſelfe of me, and as I have no other cauſe to think, procured an order in the Houſe of Lords, of the 10. <hi>Iune,</hi> 1646. contrary to the knowne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared law of <hi>England,</hi> contained in <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and <hi>the Petition of Right,</hi> and in Sir <hi>Edward Cookes</hi> expoſition of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> pag, 28. 29. 46. 50. printed by two ſpeciall Orders of this preſent Houſe of Commons, for the ſummoning me a priſoner, to anſwer a criminall charge at the Lords Bar, (who by law are none of my judges, as their Prediceſſors doe upon Record in full and open Parliament ingeniouſly confeſſe.<note n="b" place="bottom">See their confeſſion in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſe of Sir <hi>Simon de Berisford,</hi> printed in the <hi>18, 19.</hi> pages of my book, called the Oppreſſed mans oppreſſions de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. See alſo Regall tyrannie, pag. <hi>43, 44, 45. 72 73, 74, 75, 76. 86. 96. 97</hi> and Vox Plebis pag. <hi>39 40, 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> See Iudge I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nk as printed Declaration.</note> And although for gratitude ſake to them for their forementioned juſtice, <hi>I</hi> obeyed their warrant and appeared at their Bar, yet in the manner of their proceedings with me they outſtript the known rules of the law of <hi>England,</hi> and neither gave me a charge either ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ball or in writing, nor never produced either accuſer or witneſſe, but by their Speaker the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter</hi> my declared enemy, moſt inquiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tar-Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber like, preſſed me to anſwer to Interrogatories againſt my ſelfe, which I with all reſpect and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oderation told them, was againſt the tenour of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> which practice they themſelves had deeply condemned in the Star Cham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, but the 13. <hi>Feb.</hi> before in my own caſe, as by their Decree fully appeares, and given me 2000. l. dammages, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, for proceeding with me in that very way, and I told them, I hoped they would not now build up, what the other day (in my own caſe) they had deſtroyed, but no withſtanding my foreſaid malicious adverſarie the Earle of <hi>Mancheſter,</hi> preſſed me againe and againe, poſſitively to anſwer his illegall Interrogatories,<note n="c" place="bottom">See my relation of all the proceedings then in my book called the laſt mans iuſtification, dated from Newgate in Iune, <hi>1646.</hi>
               </note> and being for my refuſall likely in my own thoughts to goe to priſon, I was neceſſitated out of that duty I owe to my ſelfe and my Country, to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in a paper at their bar under my hand and Seale, containing a Proteſt againſt their juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over me, in the caſe then in controverſie betwixt us, and an appeale to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, (in the juſtification of which <hi>I</hi> will live and dye, ſtand or fall) my legall Peers and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualls, for protection, juſtice and right, againſt their illegall uſurpations, for which very paper and nothing elſe, they committed me to Newgate Priſon,<note n="d" place="bottom">As appeares by their warrant printed in the book laſt named pag in which book you may alſo read in my Proteſt. againſt the Lords, and my appeale to the Houſe of Commons.</note> from whence upon the 16. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1646. <hi>I</hi> ſent to the Houſe of Commons, my legall and formall Appeale, which they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, read, approved of, and committed it to the ſpeciall examination and tryall of a ſelect Committee, whereof Mr. <hi>Henry Martin</hi> had the Chaire, who hath failed ever ſince to make my report unto the houſe, though two ſeverall times he fully examined all my buſineſſe. But in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the bearer is in haſt and <hi>I</hi> cannot well for want of time at the preſent, particularly ſtate the reſt that hath paſt <hi>I</hi> have incloſed for your information a coppy of my wives large petition, preſented to the Houſe about <hi>September</hi> laſt<note n="e" place="bottom">Which Petition you may read in the <hi>73. 74. 75. 76.</hi> pages of Regall tyranny, &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> alſo in my own book called Londons Liberty pag. and at the laſt end of the outcryes of oppreſſed Commons.</note> which fully ſtates my caſe to that preſent, being of my own drawing up for her, upon which <hi>I</hi> had a new and very full hearing upon the 6 of <hi>November</hi> 1646 before Mr. <hi>Henry Martin,</hi> which you may at large read in my book called an
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115122:15"/>
               <hi>Annotamy of the Lords tyranny,</hi> who yet never made my report, the want of which, is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that cauſeth the continuance of my afflictions, it having been my longing and preſſing de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ever ſince to receive their determination, either to my condemnation or juſtification.</p>
            <p>My earneſt and moſt preſſing, and moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt deſire to you therefore is, to improve your ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt intereſt to get the houſe of Commons, without any further delay, to comand and order Mr. <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tin</hi> (who in a late letter to me poſſitively tells me, he hath ſince he heard my cauſe profered to make my report twenty times, but the houſe would not heare h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, to mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the report of my cauſe to them. And that upon the report they would adjudge my cauſe either to my Juſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or condemnation, (i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being all one to me in a manner which it be, ſo it be but adjudged, that ſo <hi>I</hi> may thereby know what to truſt to) for favour, mercy, pitty, or compaſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I</hi> crave none from them, but only the benefit of Law, and unſpotted juſtice, and if <hi>I</hi> have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed the Law, let them puniſh me to the utmoſt puntil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o of it, but if I have done nothing but what is juſt, legall, and honeſt (as I am ſure I have not) in this conteſt with the uſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ping and incroaching houſe of Lords, in maintaining my own juſt, legall, and heriditary libertie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and the liberties of all my fellow Commons of E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gland, which the wicked Lords themſelves, have often ſworne before God and the World, to maintane, and inviably to preſerve,) I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire imediatly without further delay, honourably to be delivered, with juſt and ample repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,<note n="*" place="bottom">But in caſe this cannot preſently be done, I deſire you to importune your honeſt Generall to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke my own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement or reaſonable ſecurity, and to give me my liberty to follow my own buſineſſe, my ſelf (which is now likely to be deſtroyed by the unworthy and uniuſt tempo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng of ſome of your great ones, with the uniuſt and tyrannicall Houſe of Lords) wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, honour no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> honeſty he cannot deny unto me, being I am now his priſoner, as he is Conſtable of the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> and ſeeing that for above this <hi>14.</hi> moneths toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>I</hi> cannot obtaine one dram of iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce nor right from the hands of the Parliament houſes at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> though I have not left any hazzardous or iuſt means unattempted, by all the friends and intereſt I have in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, either in City or Country, but am never the better, but am now likely I and mine to be murthered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the blood thirſty cruelty of the Houſe of Peers, and the wilfull and vniuſtifiable negl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gence of the ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirated Houſe of Commons; and by the cauſeleſſe mallice of ſome great ones in your Army, and in this caſe you and your Generall cannot but in iuſtice, honour and conſceience afford me ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edy rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>efe eſpecially conſidering your own often printed Declarations to vindicate the Subiects libertys, and to relieve the oppreſſed, which I am ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly informed both your Generall and your ſelves are willing to doe, and therefore I pray you ſend me the names of all or the chiefe obſtructers of my iuſt deliverance by your Generall, that ſo I may diſcover them to the whole Kingdome, to be a company of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers and Apoſtatized Lordlings, which by Gods aſſistance <hi>I</hi> am reſolved ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to doe to the purpoſe, although they be never ſo great, and although <hi>I</hi> periſh and be deſtroyed for ſo doing.</note> for all my unjuſt, and illegall barbarous ſufferings by them; without doing of which by the houſe of Commons, (for all the Lords greatneſſe and preſent pretended deſembling goodneſſe,) they doe not doe me nor the Kingdome conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rned on me, effectuall juſtice and right.</p>
            <p>So with my heartieſt and trueſt love and ſervice preſented, to you all, deſiring God to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you to keepe cloſe inviably to your ſolemn and iuſt ingagement &amp; to act vigorouſly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolvedly to the utmoſt of your power, in the wayes of unbiaſed iuſtice and honeſty, to the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and effectuall ſettlement of all the iuſt intereſts of England, and to the cruſhing of all Tyra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall uſurpations, eſpecially in the pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ant tyranizing uniuſt houſe of Lords, and to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of a brand o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eternall and everlaſting infamy to future generations, upon all thoſe, though never ſo great and guilded that viſibly and evidently already have improved their power, intereſt, and machavill pollicies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>violate, infrindg, and crample under their feet, your moſt excellent iuſt and ſolemn ingagement made, agreed unto, and generally ſubſcribed, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> New <hi>Market,</hi> 5 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1647. And to req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e all your unwearied paines and labour of love manifeſted for the iuſt deliverance of me &amp;c. ſeven told into you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own boſomes in this World, and that which is to come, and ſo I bid you fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and reſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours very much obliged to ſerve you th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> earneſtly cryes out to you for your iuſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> without which he is likely to perriſh, Iohn Lilburn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my moſt uniuſt and moſt illegall Captivity in the Tower of London</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 27. <hi>of Auguſt.</hi> 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
